Teresina Rowell Havens Papers, 1891-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Teresina R. Havens papers
1891-1994
Havens, Teresina R. (Teresina Rowell)
MS 211
8 boxes (10.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor of comparative religion; Founder, spiritual retreat Temenos, Shutesbury, MA. Included in the collection are scrapbooks from Japan and the coal mining town of Bradley, Ohio. Correspondence with family members provides insight into her personal and spiritual development. Havens' papers include dairies; Smith College student papers; published articles; teaching materials; and the papers of her mother, Teresina Peck Rowell.
Teresina Rowell was born January 13, 1909, the daughter of Wilfrid Asa Rowell, a Congregational minister, and Teresina Peck Rowell (Smith 1894). Following her graduation from Smith College in 1929, Rowell went to Europe. She traveled during the summer and then studied comparative religion at the University of London. She returned to the United States in 1931 and began study at Yale under a fellowship awarded by the National Council of Religion in Higher Education. She received a Ph.D. in comparative religion from Yale in 1933. Between 1933 and 1936 Rowell taught Sociology of Religion at Carleton College, Northfield, Minnesota. In 1936 she visited Japan to investigate the relationship between Buddhism and the Imperial (Shinto) Cult. While there, she encountered the Itto-En sect, a group of Buddhist Christians who were practicing voluntary poverty. She gave up her traveling money to the founder of the order and became an apostle and missionary. She returned to the U.S. in 1937. In 1940 she became a Quaker after working as summer staff at the Quaker retreat and study center at Pendle Hill, Wallingford, Pennsylvania. Influenced by socialist Quakers and the journal of the Quaker, John Woolman, she lived with coal-miners' families in eastern Ohio in the late-1930s. In August 1942, with three other Pendle Hill students, she moved to the black ghetto of Chester, Pennsylvania, and set up a work and prayer commune where she did volunteer housework and other manual labor for families. In 1945, Joseph Durald Havens joined the commune and he and Teresina were married in January 1947. A daughter, Lucia, was born in 1947 and a son, Wilfrid Thwing, in 1951. She was also a staff member at Pendle Hill from 1942 to 1948.
Throughout the years Teresina Havens taught religion at various colleges and universities including Beloit College (1938); Smith College (1939-42); University of Southern California (1950-51); Wilmington College (Ohio) (1954-56) and Springfield College (Massachusetts) (1968-70). She also taught philosophy at Westfield State College (Massachusetts) (1966-67). In the 1970s she taught courses at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst in their semi-autonomous experimental Project 10, which was a series of seminars, workshops, and tutorials meant to explore different ways of learning.
In 1972 the Havens set out on a five-month odyssey across the United States, visiting a number of spiritual communities. Returning to the east they purchased land in Shutesbury, Massachusetts, where they created a spiritual retreat and conference center. They named the place Temenos, a Greek word for the sacred enclosed place surrounding a temple or altar. It was incorporated in 1981 under an advisory group with the Havens as founders and program directors. They retired and moved to Oregon in 1989 where Teresina died February 14,1992.
The Teresina Rowell Havens Papers consist of 3 1/3 linear feet of correspondence, photographs, diaries, writings, memorabilia, printed material, and one audiotape. They date from 1891 to 1994 with the bulk of the material beginning in the 1930s.
Included with these papers are travel diaries, a small amount of correspondence, and writings of her mother, Teresina Peck Rowell. The Teresina Rowell Havens Papers provide an excellent insight into one women's spiritual development as well as some of the experimental teaching methods of the 1970s. Teresina's life was intentionally unconventional and her papers reflect an alternative lifestyle spanning 50 years.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Material, Memorabilia, and Photographs
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
IV. Teaching and Lecture Material
V. Subjects
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Havens Papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Teresina Rowell Havens donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection between 1986 and 1991. Additional material was donated by Marjorie Kellogg and Lenore Diane in1992.
Search Terms
Japan--description and travel--Sources; Japan--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources; New Age movement--United States--History--Sources; Religions--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Society of Friends--United States--History--Sources; Unification Church--United States--History--Sources; University of Massachusetts (Amherst, Mass.)--Faculty--History--Sources; Temenos (Shutesbury, Mass.)--History--Sources; Spirituality--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Havens, Teresina R. (Teresina Rowell); Rowell, Teresina Peck, 1872-1945
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, MEMORABILIA AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview by Dianne Hayter, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1948-94, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks from Japan, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    [See also SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE]
  - Correspondence and memorabilia from Bradley, OH, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorabilia
    - Drawings made during worship at Temenos, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1928-38, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Teresina Peck Rowell to family, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - From Teresina Rowell Havens
    - Wilfrid and Teresina Peck Rowell
      [See also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL AND MEMORABILIA]
      - 1927-45 (Box 2, Folder 2-14)
      - 1946-53, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Others, 1941-91, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Marjorie Kellogg (spiritual friend of the Universal Third Order), 1987-88 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - From friends to Teresina Rowell Havens, 1929-42, 1971-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - From Joseph and Teresina Rowell Havens
    - Lucia Havens, 1963-88, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
    - Wilfrid Thwing Havens and family, 1971-73, 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous family, 1972-87 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Friends (Christmas letters), 1973, 1990-91 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - To Joseph Havens from Gerry McFarland, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lucia Havens to Teresina and Joseph Havens, 1962-82 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - To Lucia Havens from others, 1963-64, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Wilfrid Thwing Havens to family 1963-85 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Diaries
    - Teresina Peck Rowell, 1913, 1929, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Teresina Rowell Havens
      - 1920-42 (Box 5)
      - 1943-87 (Box 6)
  - Other
    - Teresina Peck Rowell, 1891-1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Teresina Rowell Havens
      - Smith College, 1926-28 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Publications, 1931-88, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
      - "Not a Proposition But a Method--Paradoxes of Buddhism in the Classroom" (a chapter for the Festschrift for Edwin Burtt), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- SERIES IV. TEACHING AND LECTURE MATERIAL
  - University of Massachusetts, Project 10
    - Buddhism, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Death and Rebirth, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Learning Through Posture and Gesture, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Center for Interpretation of Academic and Meditative Disciplines, 1973-74 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Inquiry Program, 1978-80 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Friends Conference on Religion and Psychology (Haverford, PA), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-91, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Network On Alternative Teachings undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Self-evaluations and contracts, 1976-79 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS
  - Lucia Havens, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Quakers and Mt. Toby Friends Meeting, 1964-81, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Society for Religion in Higher Education, 1970, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Temenos, 1973-88, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)